<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Citation Style Language: An Interview with Rintze Zelle
and Ian Mulvany</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-09-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Citation styles are one of the greater mysteries for the novice
manuscript writer. There are numerous ways that authors, title, journal,
etc. can be arranged and formatted (see examples below), and in
bibliographies citations can be ordered either alphabetically or by
order of appearance in the text.</p>
<p><bold><bold>Laemmli UK</bold></bold>. Cleavage of Structural Proteins
during the Assembly of the Head of Bacteriophage T4.
<italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>. 1970;227:680-685.</p>
<p><bold><bold>U. K. Laemmli</bold></bold> (1970). ‘Cleavage of
Structural Proteins during the Assembly of the Head of Bacteriophage
T4′. <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>
<bold><bold>227</bold></bold>(5259):680-685.</p>
<p><bold><bold>U. K. Laemmli</bold></bold>,
<italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> <bold><bold>227</bold></bold>,
680 (1970).</p>
<p>Because of this complexity, it has long become impractical to format
citations manually, and formatting of citations and bibliographies is
one of the main reasons for using reference management software. I
interviewed Rintze Zelle (scientist and open source contributor) and Ian
Mulvany (vice president of new product development at Mendeley) to
better understand citation styles in general and the open source
Citation Style Language (CSL) in particular. CSL co-developers Bruce
D’Arcus and Frank Bennett provided important feedback.</p>
<sec id="1-what-is-the-citation-style-language">
  <title><bold><bold>1. What is the Citation Style
  Language?</bold></bold></title>
  <p>Rintze Zelle: Scientific literature depends heavily on proper
  referencing. However, when writing a manuscript, manually editing
  citations and bibliographies is time consuming and error prone.
  Citation styles also differ between scientific journals, so authors
  often have to switch citation styles when they submit their manuscript
  to a different journal than originally anticipated.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://citationstyles.org/">Citation
  Style Language</ext-link> (CSL) is an open XML based language meant to
  automate the formatting of citations and bibliographies. When provided
  with the metadata (title, year, authors, etc.) of the cited items
  (journal articles, books, etc.), and a CSL style, a CSL processor can
  automatically generate the bibliography and in-text citations. CSL is
  currently used by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</ext-link>,
  and both programs offer word processor plug-ins for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/word/">Microsoft
  Word</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice.org</ext-link>.
  Several other projects are working on or exploring CSL support.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-do-we-really-need-hundreds-of-citation-styles">
  <title>2. Do we really need hundreds of citation styles?</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Rintze Zelle</bold></bold>: We have asked ourselves
  this question many times over. Some variability is certainly
  warranted: numeric, author-date and footnote styles are very
  different, and each type has its own advantages and disadvantages.
  However, small variations in citation styles result in a situation
  where almost every journal or publisher has its unique style. We think
  that even with the use of automated tools like CSL, reducing the
  number of citation styles in use could result in significant cost and
  time savings in scientific publishing. But this is a problem beyond
  the scope of CSL, so our goal is simply to support all the variability
  that currently exists in citation styles.</p>
  <p><bold><bold>Ian Mulvany</bold></bold>: After working for many years
  at Springer, and then Nature, I was well aware that most large
  publishers just push submitted manuscripts out to companies in India
  where the formatting of the paper happens. The input format and
  citation formatting really doesn’t matter to most publishers. They
  just tear the submitted manuscript to pieces and rebuild it in their
  chosen XML schema.</p>
  <p>However, most people using citations are not actually submitting
  manuscripts for publication, but rather are writing term papers, or
  theses, or reports. So the weird thing is that citations started off
  as a required identifier for the literature. Google Scholar and HTTP
  URIs such as the DOI have almost totally made formatted citations
  redundant as identifiers, and yet there is still a huge user need to
  be able to format citations according to a huge variety of styles, and
  since that need is going to continue for quite a long time, it’s a
  need that we have to support.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-is-the-difference-between-csl-and-other-citation-style-systems">
  <title><bold><bold>3. What is the difference between CSL and other
  citation style systems?</bold></bold></title>
  <p>Rintze Zelle: Our main “competition” arguably comes from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.bibtex.org/">BibTeX</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.endnote.com/">EndNote</ext-link>/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.refman.com/">Reference
  Manager</ext-link>. BibTeX is a popular choice for those working with
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</ext-link>
  typesetting system, but the user base of LaTeX is relatively small and
  mostly limited to the sciences. EndNote and Reference Manager are
  commercial tools offered by Thomson Reuters. While large collections
  of citation styles are available for each program, the use of these
  styles is limited to licensed users.</p>
  <p>CSL was designed with three main goals:</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>to create an open system that is independent of the operating
      system, application or document format,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>to cover the full range of citation formatting rules in use,
      extending from the sciences to fields in the humanities as well as
      law,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>to free end users from the complex task of formatting
      citations.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Citation styles should be freely available, up to date, and
  complete. Switching between styles should be easy, and citation output
  should automatically localize to the desired language.</p>
  <p>We think we’ve come quite far toward reaching these goals with our
  most recent release, CSL 1.0. The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://citationstyles.org/downloads/specification.html">CSL
  1.0 specification</ext-link> covers a wide range of citation rules,
  and offers advanced features like automatic localization of date
  formats, terms and punctuation, support for in-field rich text and
  extensive support for the rendering and disambiguation of names. The
  first standalone CSL 1.0 processor (the JavaScript
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://bitbucket.org/fbennett/citeproc-js/">citeproc-js</ext-link>)
  is currently being integrated into both Zotero and Mendeley, and is
  receiving attention for deployment on both the client and the
  server.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-can-you-tell-me-how-csl-was-developed">
  <title>4. Can you tell me how CSL was developed?</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Rintze Zelle</bold></bold>: CSL is the brainchild of
  Bruce D’Arcus, an associate professor of Geography at Miami University
  of Ohio. The language was initially implemented for integration into
  OpenOffice.org, but only became popular in 2006 when Zotero, the first
  reference manager to use CSL, was released. In these early days major
  contributions were made to CSL by Zotero developer Simon Kornblith.
  Subsequently, the Zotero project successfully fostered an active user
  community, with many users contributing styles to a growing repository
  of CSL styles.</p>
  <p>The year 2008 was a watershed of new developments. Mendeley was
  released, the second reference manager to use CSL for its citation
  formatting. Andrea Rossato released the first standalone CSL processor
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://code.haskell.org/citeproc-hs/">citeproc-hs</ext-link>)
  for use with the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/">Pandoc</ext-link>
  text</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
