<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial Manager: Interview with Richard
Wynne</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-03-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Practically all scientific journals now use web-based systems for
paper submissions and peer review. This saves the authors a lot of time
compared to paper submissions by postal mail (until 15 years ago) or
email (until 5 years ago). Unfortunately the submission process is still
far from perfect and requires authors to spend many hours formatting
manuscripts, references and images instead of focusing on the scientific
content.</p>
<p>The tools (word processors, reference managers, graphics programs,
etc.) that most authors use to write manuscripts have become more
sophisticated every year, but often don't help much with creating
structured documents. Structure is the most important feature of a
scientific manuscript (title, authors, abstract, materials and methods,
references, etc.), and this is much more relevant than the layout
(fonts, page margins, etc.).</p>
<p>There are two different approaches to create structured manuscripts.
Authors could use tools such as the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/11/07/interview-with-pablo-fernicola">Microsoft
Word Article Authoring Add-in</ext-link> or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/02/27/lemon8-xml-interview-with-mj-suhonos">Lemon8-XML</ext-link>
and submit structured manuscripts in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://www.inera.com/nlmresources.shtml">NLM
DTD</ext-link> XML format. Or journal submission systems could improve
the process of creating structured manuscripts from standard word
processor files (e.g. Microsoft Word). To better understand the second
option, I asked Richard Wynne from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://www.editorialmanager.com/homepage/about.html">Aries</ext-link>
a few questions about
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://www.editorialmanager.com/homepage/home.htm">Editorial
Manager</ext-link>.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-editorial-manager-is-and-does">
  <title><italic><italic>1. Can you describe what Editorial Manager is
  and does?</italic></italic></title>
  <p>Editorial Manager is like plumbing for scholarly publishing. It
  manages the flow of scholarly manuscripts from submission to
  acceptance. Like good plumbing it should be invisible, reliable and
  afford some luxury.</p>
  <p>While most of us could theoretically do our own plumbing, we
  usually discover that it's better to pay a professional. It's the same
  with online peer review systems. Most scholarly societies, publishers
  and university presses could develop and host their own workflow
  systems; but have discovered that it's less messy and less expensive
  to use a commercial solution such as Editorial Manager.</p>
  <p>More than 3,100 journals from 150 publishers have adopted Editorial
  Manager. In the interest of fairness, I should mention other available
  solutions:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://pkp.sfu.ca/?q=ojs">Open
      Journal Systems</ext-link>,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://scholarone.com/products/manuscript/">Manuscript
      Central</ext-link>,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://www.ejpress.com/index.shtml">eJournal
      Press</ext-link>,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://benchpress.highwire.org/">BenchPress</ext-link>.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Thanks to a healthy competitive environment, online peer review is
  one of the most innovative areas of scholarly publishing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-in-what-document-formats-can-manuscripts-be-submitted-to-editorial-manager-can-manuscripts-be-submitted-from-online-word-processors-such-as-google-docs">
  <title>2. In what document formats can manuscripts be submitted to
  Editorial Manager? Can manuscripts be submitted from online word
  processors such as Google Docs?</title>
  <p>There are virtually no technical limitations on the types of files
  that can be loaded into Editorial Manager. However:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Only some file types (such as Office, LaTeX, and image formats
      etc.) can be automatically converted to PDF format. Other types of
      file (e.g. Video or audio files) can be uploaded and are
      accessible during workflow from links in the generated PDF, and
      from the manuscript file inventory for authorized editors.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Superimposed on this technical handling is journal policy.
      Acceptable submission items (e.g. manuscript, data set etc.) are
      configured by the journal according to their idiosyncratic
      workflow preferences. So while one journal using Editorial Manager
      may permit the upload of supplemental data, another may choose not
      to make this option available.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>We have not interfaced with Google Docs at an API level, but this
  would become a priority if large numbers of authors found it a
  productive authoring tool for scholarly manuscripts. In the interim
  Google Docs provides many supported download file format options such
  as RTF.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-why-do-most-publishers-prefer-not-to-have-manuscripts-submitted-as-pdf-file-s-">
  <title>3. Why do most publishers prefer not to have manuscripts
  submitted as PDF file(s)?</title>
  <p>Editorial Manager does support upload of manuscripts in PDF format.
  However many publishers discourage this practice for good reasons:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Some journals ask reviewers to directly edit the manuscript in
      word processing format – obviously not possible if the author
      uploads a PDF.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>If the manuscript is accepted, the publisher will need access
      to original source files to undertake copy editing, image
      formatting, composition etc. Obtaining source files up-front
      allows the publisher to accelerate the workflow and eliminates the
      time-consuming and cumbersome step of obtaining source files from
      the author after acceptance. Publishers that do accept PDF
      submissions must ensure that subsequently submitted source files
      match the revised manuscript that was accepted by the editors as
      an error prone and unnecessary step.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>It's unfortunate that publishers don't take the time to explain
  their reasoning regarding PDF submissions. This contributes to the
  scholar street wisdom that publishers are out of touch.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-can-manuscripts-be-transferred-from-preprint-servers-such-as-arxiv-or-nature-preceedings">
  <title>4. Can manuscripts be transferred from preprint servers such as
  arXiv or Nature Preceedings?</title>
  <p>Yes, manuscripts can be directly transferred from the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://arxiv.org/">arXiv</ext-link>
  server by entering the appropriate arXiv number during the submission
  process. Editorial Manager then automatically collects the source
  files from the arXiv server. The feature is journal configurable.
  We have not yet implemented a similar feature for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://precedings.nature.com/">Nature
  Precedings</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-how-does-editorial-manager-support-the-nlm-dtd-format-can-manuscripts-be-submitted-in-that-format">
  <title>5. How does Editorial Manager support the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150908031524/http://www.inera.com/nlmresources.shtml">NLM
  DTD</ext-link> format? Can manuscripts be submitted in that
  format?</title>
  <p>Editorial Manager does process files with structured DTDs, but
  that's not really the point of your question. Here's the issue:
  reliably structured manuscripts theoretically present workflow
  benefits:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>During submission, manuscript metadata could be automatically
      harvested from the file, thereby avoiding author re-keying of
      title, abstract, etc.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Journal styling and composition could be applied automatically,
      thereby avoiding manual steps currently required to structure
      unformatted manuscripts – a massive cost and time saving.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Today these benefits remain largely theoretical because they depend
  entirely on authors uploading standardized, structured manuscripts.
  The question is: who should have ultimate responsibility for
  manuscript structure quality? In my opinion not authors – their
  primary focus should be manuscript content not manuscript format. Part
  of the publisher's role is to take care of manuscript structuring.
  Trying to offload this responsibility to authors is not a good use of
  their time.</p>
  <p>E</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
