<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>I was at SciBarCamp Palo Alto</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-07-10">
<day>10</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://www.scibarcamp.org/SciBarCamp_Palo_Alto">SciBarCamp
Palo Alto</ext-link> took place July 8-9 in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://www.iftf.org/">Institute
for the Future</ext-link>. I came right from the airport and arrived too
late for the general introductions and session suggestions. But there
was time for a little break before Sean Mooney started his keynote
lecture.</p>
<sec id="keynote-biomedical-research-in-the-age-of-cyberinfrastructure">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://ff.im/4YEeQ">Keynote:
  Biomedical Research in the Age of
  Cyberinfrastructure</ext-link></title>
  <p>Sean Mooney</p>
  <p>Sean Mooney
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://www.buckinstitute.org/theInstitute/news.asp?id=31">just
  recently joined the Buck Institute for Age Research</ext-link> as
  director of their bioinformatics core. He was talking both about his
  extensive experience building web-based bioinformatics tools, but also
  about
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://laboratree.org/">Laboratree</ext-link>,
  a social networking tool for scientists with a focus on research
  management. The key argument he was trying to make is that we have a
  large number of online tools to store and analyze the data of our
  scientific experiments, but that there is still not enough effort to
  connect these tools. The infrasctructure networks that exist (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/https://cabig.nci.nih.gov/">caBIG</ext-link>)
  usually focus on one particular domain (cancer research in this case),
  and the 27 NIH institutes all have their own approach to informatics.
  Researchers and administrators have a very different approach to
  online tools. Whereas researchers want to analyze data, administrators
  focus more on the much broader picture, e.g. asset management.
  Administrators often misjudge their needs for the needs of the
  scientist. Scientists often mistake today's needs for tomorrow's
  needs.</p>
  <p>Sean also talked about his experience building
  <italic>Laboratree</italic>. He thinks that the social networking for
  scientists killer app is one that people “have to use” not “like to
  use”, and that successful tools are simple and start with a
  preexisting community.</p>
  <p>After the keynote we had un-dinner in smaller groups, and I went to
  bed after being up for 24 hours thanks to the 9 hour time difference.
  The next day we had the unconference sessions suggested the day
  before, and I talk a little bit about the sessions I attended. The
  rest of the sessions are well documented in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://friendfeed.com/scibarcamp">SciBarCamp
  FriendFeed group</ext-link> and on
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://twitter.com/#search?q=%23sbcPA">Twitter</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="open-source-textbooks">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://ff.im/50EdW">Open
  Source Textbooks</ext-link></title>
  <p>Chris Patil</p>
  <p>This was a great brainstorming session. We agreed that – with very
  few exceptions – there is no financial incentive for scientists to
  write textbooks. The main motivation is reputation, and we thought
  that the lack of return on textbook authoring is an opportunity for
  new approaches. The concept of Open Access textbooks is a social
  problem (e.g. who pays for the textbook, what are the author
  incentives when there is a long list of contributors), and not a
  technical problem.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://ocw.mit.edu/OcwWeb/web/home/home/index.htm">OpenCourseWare</ext-link>
  was mentioned as a great educational resource that overlaps in intent
  with Open Access textbooks. Sean Mooney and Cameron Neylon mention the
  often unsolved copyright issues when creating Open Access material,
  and this includes potential issues with proper attribution with the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://creativecommons.org/">Creative
  Commons</ext-link> license when reusing material. We briefly talked
  about document formats (where PDF probably is still important), and
  that we probably need to print most of the textbooks, at least until
  eBook readers become cheaper.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="personal-genomics">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://ff.im/50N35">Personal
  Genomics</ext-link></title>
  <p>Melanie Swan</p>
  <p>This for me was a great introduction to the topic, and the main
  emphasis of the session was probably on the consumer perspective. The
  first ever consumer genomics conference
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://www.consumergeneticsshow.com/">was
  held in Boston last month</ext-link>. One important, and still only
  partly solved issue is huge amount of data generated, especially if we
  take into account not only genetics, but also epigenetic changes, and
  the fact that not all cells of an individual are genetically identical
  (which is true especially in cancer). The technology is changing
  rapidly and the cost of sequencing a whole genome of an individual is
  constantly coming down. We talked about a few examples of genes that
  are already useful to test, one prominent example being
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://rbaltman.wordpress.com/2009/05/21/cms-made-a-mistake-in-not-approving-genetics-for-warfarin/">CYP2C9</ext-link>
  and warfarin (an anticoagulant) metabolism. Many chronic disease
  conditions are multigenetic, and therefore it is usually risk
  assessment rather than yes/no answers. Some personalized genetics
  testing companies are
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://www.navigenics.com/">Navigenics</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://www.decode.com/">Decode</ext-link>,
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/https://www.23andme.com/">23andMe</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="article-level-metric-from-the-plos-perspective">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://ff.im/50Wty">Article
  level metric from the PLoS perspective</ext-link></title>
  <p>Peter Binfield</p>
  <p>Peter started the session by addressing the problem: how do you
  access the worth of impact of journal articles, and at what level do
  we measure this: journal, research institution, individual researcher?
  he then went over currently used article level metrics that fall into
  six areas:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>citation metrics</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>usage metrics</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>expert rankings (Faculty of 1000)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Conversations (blogs, media coverage, comments)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>social bookmarking (citeULike etc)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Other cool stuff (geotagging of authors, etc.)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>In this broader context article-level metrics can be seen as
  post-publication peer review. Much of this is still ongoing,
  ResearchBlogging.org is for example bulding an API so that blog posts
  about PLoS articles can be tracked. In August PLoS One will add
  information about usage statistics to all their papers. Because usage
  statistics are currently not widely available, this give a push to the
  role of usage statistics in evaluating a paper. Future work at PLoS
  will include better integration with Mendeley, Zotero, CiteULike and
  similar services. We briefly talked about the relative little use of
  commenting and tagging at PLoS One, and some people in the audience
  felt that we need automated tools (e.g. by looking at what papers are
  bookmarked or stored in Mendeley) rather than user generated
  content.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="spinning-science-the-good-and-the-bad-of-media-sensationalism">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161110193313/http://ff.im/51cld">Spinning
  Science: The good and the bad of media
  sensationalism</ext-link></title>
  <p><italic>Naomi Most, Kiki Sanford</italic></p>
  <p>Naomi and Kiki started the session by putting up the provocative
  hypothesis that sensationalism is the way to report science. They cite
  Edwin Slosson who in 1921 said <italic>Our best plan is probably to
  try to crowd out falsehood by truth and to present scientific
  information in a way that will be at least as attractive as the
  misinformation that now holds the field.</italic> They point out that
  there are different realms of science communication, including</p>
  <p>science for scientists</p>
  <p>science for scientists working in different fields</p>
  <p>s</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
