<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Victor Henning from
Mendeley</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-09-05">
<day>5</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3120/2827515376_ac2f0d81a1_o.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>In the last few months we have seen an ever increasing number of new
social networking (Web 2.0) sites for scientists. Good Web 2.0 tools for
scientists primarily try to solve a problem. But by adding a social
aspect, they will gain useful features that would otherwise not be
possible.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/U27CE62BB"><bold>Eva
Amsen</bold></ext-link> has recently written a great blog post about
this<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn1"><bold>1</bold></ext-link></sup>.
Many of these new services have overlapping functions, e.g. almost all
of them allow the user to maintain a list of contacts. This raises two
questions:</p>
<list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
    <p>Which of these sites has (or have) the features that I’m most
    interested in?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Do any of these sites work with the commonly used desktop tools
    and with each other, so that I don’t have to maintain duplicate
    information, e.g. the list of my publications?</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/U42E63119"><bold>Cameron
Neylon</bold></ext-link> in August posted an open letter to the
developers of these
sites<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn2"><bold>2</bold></ext-link></sup>
and also started a comprehensive
list<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn3"><bold>3</bold></ext-link></sup>.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/http-network-nature-comprofilegerrymck"><bold>Gerry
McKiernan</bold></ext-link> <bold></bold> collects information about
social networking sites for scientists on his SciTechNet
blog<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn4"><bold>4</bold></ext-link></sup>.
Mendeley<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn5"><bold>5</bold></ext-link></sup>
is one of these new Web 2.0 sites for scientists (they launched in
August), and I spoke with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/U4C4A58A2%5B6"><bold>Victor
Henning</bold></ext-link>, one of the founders of Mendeley, about
it.</p>
<p><bold>1. Can you describe what Mendeley is and does?</bold>
Mendeley is actually two things: Mendeley Desktop and Mendeley Web.
Mendeley Desktop is free academic software (available for Windows, Mac
and Linux) for managing &amp; sharing research papers. Mendeley Web lets
you back up your research papers online, shows you research trends in
your academic discipline, and connects you to like-minded
researchers.</p>
<p><bold>2. What is the connection to Last.fm?</bold>
There is a conceptual as well as a personal connection. Conceptually, in
the long run Mendeley aims to do for research what Last.fm did for
music. For those of your readers who don’t know Last.fm, this is how it
works: When you install Last.fm’s desktop software on your computer, it
will monitor which music you listen to and automatically build a profile
of your musical taste on the Last.fm website. The website then
recommends you music that you might like, shows you statistics about the
most popular songs and artists in your favourite genre, and lets you
discover people with a similar taste in music. By aggregating the
listening habits and tags of its 20 million users, Last.fm has managed
to create the largest ontological classification (and the largest open
database) of music in the world – it would be great if we could achieve
the same for research papers.</p>
<p>So, if you install Mendeley Desktop on your computer, you can manage
and share research papers on your machine, but you can also upload your
papers to your private account on Mendeley Web to access them online.
Mendeley Web anonymously aggregates the metadata of these papers to
generate statistics about the most popular authors and papers in your
research discipline, and – in the future – generates recommendations for
papers which you might like. One thing that we handle very differently
from Last.fm is privacy: The Last.fm website lets everyone know which
music you listen to, whereas Mendeley Web keeps all your research data
in your private account which can’t be accessed by anyone else. The
conceptual parallels between Last.fm and Mendeley are outlined in more
detail in a talk I gave both at the EuroScience Open Forum 2008 in
Barcelona and at the Southampton Open Science
Workshop<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn7"><bold>7</bold></ext-link></sup>.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3129/2822784112_f01ed9673b_o.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Besides the conceptual similarities, the personal connection to
Last.fm is Dr. Stefan Glänzer. He was Last.fm’s first investor and
executive chairman, and now has the same role at Mendeley. My co-founder
Jan and I first met him back in 2003, when he was a guest lecturer in
Entrepreneurship at our university, the WHU
Vallendar<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn8"><bold>8</bold></ext-link></sup>,
and we contributed a case study to the book he published together with
our professors. So when we were looking for funding, we approached him
again in June 2007, he was fascinated by the idea of Mendeley and
luckily decided to join us. He also brought us in touch with the former
founding engineers of Skype, who became investors as well.</p>
<p><bold>3. What are your responsibilities within Mendeley?</bold>
I do most of the conceptual work behind Mendeley and write the
specifications for our developers: What is the vision of Mendeley
Desktop and Mendeley Web in the long term, which features should we
develop next to get there, how does each feature work in detail, right
down to questions like “where do we place this button and how do we
label it?”. So you can blame me for all the usability problems you might
encounter.</p>
<p>I’m also responsible for staying in touch with the academic community
and incorporating its wishes into the Mendeley development roadmap,
which has the enjoyable side effect that I get to travel to all these
wonderful academic conferences. Next week, I’ll be at the Science in the
21st Century conference at the Perimeter Institute for Theoretical
Physics,
Waterloo/Ontario<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn9"><bold>9</bold></ext-link></sup>.</p>
<p><bold>4. What did you do before starting to work for Mendeley?</bold>
Until a little more than a year ago, I thought I’d pursue an academic
career – I’m currently finishing my Ph.D. on decision-making and choice
at the Bauhaus-University of Weimar. I’ve been saying “currently
finishing” for almost a year now, but I’m hopeful that I’ll manage to
submit my thesis by the end of this year :-) Prior to that, I’ve worked
in film production and the music industry a lot, and I opened a
café/bar<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn10"><bold>10</bold></ext-link></sup>
opposite the WHU in parallel to w</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
