<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Geoffrey Bilder</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-02-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Almost exactly two years ago,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/"><bold>CrossRef</bold></ext-link>
invited a number of people to discuss unique identifiers for researchers
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/CrossTech/2007/02/crossref_author_id_meeting.html"><bold>CrossRef
Author ID meeting</bold></ext-link>). One year ago Thomson Reuters
launched <bold>ResearcherID</bold>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/01/21/thomson-scientific-launches-researcherid-to-uniquely-identify-authors"><bold>Thomson
Scientific launches ResearcherID to uniquely identify
authors</bold></ext-link>). And two months ago Phil Bourne and Lynn Fink
wrote about this topic in a  <bold>PLoS Computational Biology</bold>
paper
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000247"><bold>I
Am Not a Scientist, I Am a Number</bold></ext-link>).</p>
<p>So it comes as no surprise that we also talked about author
identifiers at the recent
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki/"><bold>ScienceOnline09</bold></ext-link>
meeting in North Carolina (both in the session
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki/Reputation_authority_and_incentives/"><bold>Impact
Factors and researcher incentives</bold></ext-link> and over drinks
afterwards).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/U42E63119/profile"><bold>Cameron
Neylon</bold></ext-link> wrote down his thoughts after the meeting in a
blog post
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2009/01/20/a-specialist-openid-service-to-provide-unique-researcher-ids/"><bold>A
specialist OpenID service to provide unique researcher
IDs?</bold></ext-link>), and this resulted in
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://friendfeed.com/e/c1fd00ec-15f9-d894-4ea9-4ffeaac5ae28/A-specialist-OpenID-service-to-provide-unique"><bold>a
very interesting</bold></ext-link> discussion on
<bold>FriendFeed</bold>. And at about the same time both
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/jandot/profile"><bold>Jan
Aerts</bold></ext-link>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://saaientist.blogspot.com/2009/01/who-o-o-are-you-who-who-who-who.html"><bold>Who-o-o
are you? Who who? Who who?</bold></ext-link>) and Christopher Leonard
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://blogs.openaccesscentral.com/blogs/pmcblog/entry/some_thoughts_on_unique_author"><bold>Some
thoughts on unique author IDs</bold></ext-link>) independently wrote
blog posts about the same topic. This week
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/U42E63119/profile"><bold>Cameron
Neylon</bold></ext-link> summarized the discussion in another blog post
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2009/02/15/contributor-ids-an-attempt-to-aggregate-and-integrate/"><bold>Contributor
IDs – an attempt to aggregate and integrate</bold></ext-link>).</p>
<p>Science bloggers have put a lot of thought into the idea of a unique
author identifier and I’ve collected more reading material about author
ID at <bold>Connotea</bold> using the tag
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.connotea.org/tag/authorid"><bold>authorid</bold></ext-link>.
But I was also very curious to learn more about the work that has
already been done. That’s why I asked
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/gbilder/profile"><bold>Geoffrey
Bilder</bold></ext-link> from <bold>CrossRef</bold> a few questions. In
the end Geoffrey talked not only about author identifiers, but also
about CrossRef, DOIs and many other aspects of scholarly publishing.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-crossref-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what CrossRef is and does?</title>
  <p>Let me start with what it does because this is a little less likely
  to make your eyes glaze-over.</p>
  <p>CrossRef was originally founded by scholarly publishers to fight
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Link_rot"><bold>link-rot</bold></ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Web links have a half-life of about six years. That is, after six
  years a link is likely to break because the content that it pointed to
  has been moved. To a lay-audience this might be a mere annoyance, but
  to scholarly and professional publishers broken links are anathema.
  The scholarly record is built on a foundation of links in the form of
  citations. If these online citation links break, the online scholarly
  citation record breaks.
  But surely fighting link-rot should be simple, right? After all, the
  glory of the web is its decentralized architecture, one in which the
  domain name that you own can be used as a namespace for identifiers.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee"><bold>Tim
  Berners-Lee</bold></ext-link> has said that “cool URIs never die”.
  Aren’t “persistent URIs” merely a matter of being disciplined in the
  way that you mint URIs and in being conscientious about sensibly
  redirecting URIs when things change location on your web server?</p>
  <p>Well, certainly the majority of broken links on the web are the
  result of careless web administrators not taking the time to structure
  and redirect their web site’s URIs properly, but there are a
  significant percentage of links that will break despite the best
  efforts of webmasters. This is because in some cases the domain name
  in the link will change, and in these cases the whole “domain name as
  URI minting name-space” starts to crumble. When otherwise sensible
  technorati refer to “owning” a domain name, it makes me want to stick
  forks in my eyeballs. We do not “own” domain names. At best, we only
  lease them and there are manifold ways in which we could lose control
  of a domain name – through litigation, through forgetfulness, through
  poverty, through voluntary transfer, etc. Once you don’t control a
  domain name anymore, then you can’t control your domain-name-based
  persistent identifiers either.</p>
  <p>Incidentally, another technorati meme that makes me want to
  self-harm with cutlery is the notion that “persistent identifiers
  don’t matter in the age of the search engine. If a link breaks, we can
  just find the content again wherever it has moved.” This, naturally,
  is the self-serving argument often used by Google and it’s starry-eyed
  acolytes. Even just few minutes’ reflection reveals the gaping hole in
  this approach.</p>
  <p>The hole is this – how do you cite a specific copy of something if
  there are multiple <bold>almost identical</bold> copies of it located
  in different places? For instance, lets say there are 2 copies (X and
  Y) of an article which only differ in a few paragraphs, but those few
  paragraphs are crucial and likely to change the reader’s
  interpretation of the work. How, in a world where persistent linking
  is maintained by search engines, do you create a citation link to
  article X instead of article Y? To create a search-based link that is
  more likely to resolve to article X, you would essentially have to
  encode the entire article in the search URI! Even this wouldn’t
  guarantee you that the link directed a future reader to article X
  first; it is still possible that article Y might end up getting a
  higher ranking because more people have linked to it and it therefore
  has a higher page-rank (or equivalent). Believe me, even variations of
  the search engine scenario (using document hashes for citations,
  pingbacks, etc.) quickly unravel after a little reflection.</p>
  <p>This is all a long-winded and ranty way of saying that the issue of
  persistent identifiers on the web is just a wee bit more complex than
  most people think. So how does CrossRef address the persistent
  identifier issue?</p>
  <p>From our perspective, the persistent identifier problem is much
  more a social problem than a technical one.</p>
  <p>In fact, the technical part of our service is relatively
  straightforward. CrossRef provides a level of indirection (i.e. a
  pointer) between an identifier and a URL. When publishers put
  something online, they assign a CrossRef
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.doi.org/"><bold>Digital
  Object Identifier</bold></ext-link> (DOI) to it and submit a record
  for that item with CrossRef. The record includes the CrossRef DOI,
  basic bibliographic metadata for the content and a URL that points to
  the current location of the content. People citing the publisher’s
  content are encouraged to use the CrossRef DOI for the citation
  instead of the publisher’s URL. When a researcher clicks on a CrossRef
  DOI, the CrossRef service redirects the URL to whatever URL the
  publisher has currently registered for that CrossRef DOI. This means
  that the publisher can update their CrossRef DOI record to point to a
  completely new URI (including a new domain name) and any CrossRef DOI
  citations will continue to work. We provide a few other services based
  on this infrastructure too. So, for instance, we can resolve an
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.oclc.org/research/projects/openurl/default.htm"><bold>OpenURL</bold></ext-link>
  to a CrossRef DOI (by querying the publisher-submitted bibliographic
  metadata), resolve a free-text query to a CrossRef DOI and we can also
  return bibliographic metadata instead of redirecting if that is what
  the user wants.</p>
  <p>So-far, so good, but this isn’t anything that couldn’t be
  accomplished using other redirection tools such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.purl.org/"><bold>PURLs</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.handle.net/"><bold>CNRI
  Handles</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=xri"><bold>XRIs</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://numly.com/numly/default.asp"><bold>NUmly
  Numbers</bold></ext-link>, etc.? The crucial question to ask of any
  such service is, “what guarantees that the publisher will actually
  update their URL pointers?” If the publisher doesn’t update these
  pointers, then the links will break anyway. It isn’t enough that a
  publisher decides to use PURLs, if they then don’t update their PURLs-
  in perpetuity.</p>
  <p>This is where it is important to explain the organizational
  structure and the social effect that this has on the service.</p>
  <p>CrossRef was founded as a non-profit, membership organization for
  publishers. Note that we are entirely catholic in our definition of
  what a publisher is, so our membership includes commercial publishers,
  non-profit publishers, open access publishers, institutional
  repositories, NGOs and IGOs, Video publishers, Wiki-based publishers,
  etc. We are also open to publishers of all disciplines (humanities,
  social sciences, sciences, professional), geographies and content
  types (journals, books, database records, videos, etc.)</p>
  <p>In practice, what unites our membership is a concern that their
  content should be considered worthy of trust by professional
  researchers. One way in which researchers assess the trustworthiness
  of content is by determining how it sits within the scholarly record.
  Does it provide evidence for its assertions in citations? Do other
  people cite it?</p>
  <p>When a publisher joins CrossRef, they agree to a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/02publishers/59pub_rules.html"><bold>set
  of enforceable terms and conditions</bold></ext-link> that govern the
  way in which they use CrossRef’s persistent citation infrastructure.
  Specifically, they agree to:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Register DOIs within a week of something being published
      online</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Update the URLs associated with a DOI when said URLs change</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Link citations in their content via the DOI</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>In joining CrossRef they also agree that CrossRef can fine them or
  throw them out of the service if they do not meet the terms and
  conditions of the service. Note that the penalty of being thrown out
  can be quite severe as it effectively means that the publisher would
  become invisible in the online scholarly citation record. In short,
  the system has a built-in social feedback loop that strongly enforces
  good citizenship.</p>
  <p>As I said, the technical infrastructure of CrossRef is pretty
  mundane, and it is the social aspect of the service that does the most
  to guarantee the persistency of CrossRef citation links.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-are-your-responsibilities-within-crossref">
  <title>2. What are your responsibilities within CrossRef?</title>
  <p>Thinking of, gathering the requirements for, designing and (most
  importantly) launching new services.</p>
  <p>Last year we launched a plagiarism detection service called
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/crosscheck.html"><bold>CrossCheck</bold></ext-link>.
  This year I am working on Contributor ID, another project tentatively
  named CrossMark and a bunch of smaller projects designed to encourage
  the use of DOIs in citations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-for-crossref">
  <title>3. What did you do before starting to work for
  CrossRef?</title>
  <p>In the early nineties Allen Renear and I co-founded Brown
  University’s Scholarly Technology Group, where we were charged with
  providing advanced consulting and support to Brown’s research
  community. In the mid-nineties I grew tired of the politics, resource
  constraints and institutional paralysis that seems to grip so many
  universities and I decided to do something as far away from the
  academic sphere as possible. In short, I worked at a management
  consultancy doing R&amp;D for their IT group. In 2000 I was lured into
  managing the web development efforts for an Information Architecture
  firm called Dynamic Diagrams. In 2001 we were bought by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.ingentaconnect.com/"><bold>Ingenta</bold></ext-link>
  in the UK. I became Ingenta’s CTO and I moved to Oxford in 2002. I
  left Ingenta in 2005, did a brief spell of consulting for publishers
  in 2006 and joined CrossRef in 2007.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-are-your-thoughts-on-how-an-author-identifier-should-look-like">
  <title>4. What are your thoughts on how an author identifier should
  look like?</title>
  <p>First of all, I think we need to stop talking about “author”
  identifiers. One of the first requirements we found when interviewing
  publishers, researchers and librarians is that we would ideally like
  to be able to identify any party who contributes to the scholarly
  literature in any way. That is, we would also like to be able to
  identify reviewers, editors, correspondents, bloggers, commenters,
  etc. This is why we have taken to calling our project the “CrossRef
  Contributor ID” project. This isn’t just playing with words either.
  For instance, as soon as you start thinking about things like “how do
  you accommodate reviewers” in this system you need to think of things
  like pseudo-anonymity. That is, you want somebody to be able to get
  credit for doing reviews in a way that doesn’t necessarily reveal who
  reviewed what. In turn, the pay-off for designing a system whereby
  anonymous reviewers might be credited with reviews could be profound.
  It might ultimately result in researchers having much more incentive
  to review if reviewing were something that could be counted and rated
  in the same way that authorship is.</p>
  <p>Second, I think that people conflate a lot of issues when they talk
  about “author identifiers” [sic]. Are they talking about the simple
  token used (e.g. a unique string or a number assigned to an individual
  like a social security number), are they talking about an
  authentication mechanism (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://openid.net/what/"><bold>OpenID</bold></ext-link>,
  <bold>Shibbol</bold></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
