<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Lemon8-XML: Interview with MJ Suhonos</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-02-27">
<day>27</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Finishing an exciting research project and writing it up in a paper
are the first two steps in getting your work published. The next two
steps – submitting your paper to a journal and getting it through the
review process – have changed dramatically in the last 10-15 years. No
longer do we have to print out our manuscript using one of the few
available laser printers in the department, paste our gel pictures on
cardboard and number the figures with Letraset. And then send it off
with the mail. And then repeat the process for every revision of the
manuscript.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.flickr.com/photos/synaptichappenings/2276034665/">Flickr
  Photo</ext-link> by synaptic.happenings.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/02/2276034665_456342fb50_n.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Now of course we submit our manuscripts online using a manuscript
submission system such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.editorialmanager.com/homepage/home.htm">Editorial
Manager</ext-link> or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.ejpress.com/index.shtml">eJournalPress</ext-link>.
Which is not to say that the process is necessarily easy or fun. Many of
us can tell stories of spending hours or whole days until the manuscript
is finally submitted. We struggle with the conversion of the different
parts of the manuscript into a single PDF file, have problems with
fonts, have to deal with different graphics formats (e.g. PDF, JPEG,
EPS, TIFF), don’t use the correct style for our references, etc.</p>
<p>The flip side of this is the time and money spent at the journal to
format your accepted manuscript into something that can be turned into a
journal article published online or in print.</p>
<p>Some of these problems wouldn’t exist if we used a common document
format for manuscript writing, manuscript revisions and manuscript
printing and online viewing. That common document format does exist and
is called
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/">NLM
Journal Publishing DTD</ext-link> (and no, it’s not LaTex). This
document format is used in the workflow of many journals, but until now
has rarely been used by authors. Last November
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/11/07/interview-with-pablo-fernicola">I
talked with Pablo Fermicola</ext-link> about a free tool that allows
Microsoft Word to save manuscripts in that format
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.microsoft.com/DOWNLOADS/details.aspx?FamilyID=09c55527-0759-4d6d-ae02-51e90131997e&amp;displaylang=en">Microsoft
Word Authoring Add-In</ext-link>).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.inera.com/extylesinfo.shtml#NLM">eXtyles
NLM</ext-link> is another tool for Microsoft Word with similar
functionality.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/lemon8">Lemon8-XML</ext-link>
takes a different approach in helping academic authors convert their
manuscripts into the NLM DTD format. Version 1.0 of the software
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/node/1891">was
released today</ext-link>, so this was a great opportunity to talk with
the lead developer <italic><italic>MJ Suhonos</italic></italic> about
Lemon8-XML.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-lemon8-xml-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what Lemon8-XML is and does?</title>
  <p>Lemon8-XML is a freely-available, open source web application that
  aims to help academic authors and editors convert scholarly articles
  from layout formats like Microsoft Word to structured XML formats
  without requiring a great deal of knowledge of XML or the schema that
  they’re working with. It’s based on the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://opendocument.xml.org/overview">OpenDocument</ext-link>
  format internally, and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/">NLM
  Journal Publishing DTD</ext-link> as the default export format.</p>
  <p>Originally, Lemon8-XML came from a bunch of scripts that performed
  a series of tasks:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>convert an author’s article from a myriad of document formats
      to OpenDocument,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>parse the article and try to extract metadata, determine
      section structure based on layout information, and parse citations
      into their disparate elements,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>export this semantic data as XML.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>The work to date on Lemon8-XML has been building these functions
  into an easy-to-use web UI that also provides some editing facilities;
  for example, to fix problems from incomplete or incorrect parsing. One
  of the most promising features of Lemon8-XML is its ability to parse
  citations in a wide range of formats, and automatically try to correct
  or enhance them by searching for their complete records in, eg.
  PubMed, CrossRef, and WorldCat.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-are-the-advantages-of-using-lemon8-xml-over-traditional-word-processors-such-as-microsoft-word">
  <title>2. What are the advantages of using Lemon8-XML over traditional
  word processors such as Microsoft Word?</title>
  <p>I should start by clarifying that Lemon8-XML wasn’t really intended
  to be used as a word processor, but rather a conversion tool to be
  used after the writing was done. This was to fit in with existing
  practices, where authors upload papers to a journal and the editing is
  done afterwards. Of course, the advent of online word processors
  challenges this notion, and has caused us to think differently about
  the editing aspects of Lemon8-XML. Cross-platform deployment and
  online collaboration are things that obviously the web is great for.
  An author could, for example, upload a paper to Lemon8-XML, and work
  together with an editor on that same copy, regardless of what desktop
  tools they have. One advantage of this idea is that the burden of work
  is shared between more people, whether that’s an author and a
  copyeditor, or multiple editors. This is a big deal for small journals
  who don’t have funds for dedicated staff.</p>
  <p>Within PKP in general, we also try to keep the requirements for our
  software as low as possible, both technically and financially. So, for
  journals like
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.openmedicine.ca/">Open
  Medicine</ext-link>, who are entirely volunteer-run, paying $230 per
  copy for Microsoft Word on each computer actually represents a
  significant cost. Using OpenOffice on the desktop and a single copy of
  Lemon8-XML on a server — both of which are free — lets them spend this
  out-of-pocket expense on other things to keep their journal alive and
  growing. Microsoft Word also has an unfortunate history of being
  variable and inconsistent across platforms and versions. We wanted to
  help people escape that, which is one of the reasons for converting
  everything to OpenDocument as early as possible. In addition,
  stewarding documents through an online workflow can be a laborious and
  frustrating process, so the possibility for journals to make the
  editing process more centralized and interactive by integrating
  Lemon8-XML is a compelling one.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-how-does-lemon8-xml-compare-to-the-microsoft-word-article-authoring-add-in-that-also-produces-nlm-journal-publishing-dtd-output">
  <title>3. How does Lemon8-XML compare to the Microsoft Word Article
  Authoring Add-In, that also produces NLM Journal Publishing DTD
  output?</title>
  <p>In many ways, we’re working in parallel with Pablo Fermicola’s
  group at Microsoft —
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://perspectives.on10.net/blogs/jonudell/Word-for-scientific-publishing/">they’re
  basically building an editor</ext-link> for placing a structured NLM
  schema on top of the Microsoft WordML (DOCX) XML format, while
  Lemon8-XML places the NLM schema on top of the OpenDocument (ODT) XML
  format. Of course, there’s nothing saying that Lemon8-XML couldn’t be
  modified to read DOCX files generated with the Article Authoring
  Add-In or vice-versa. This difference is really a reflection of the
  two competing standards, and</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
