<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Nine simple ways to make it easier to (re)use your
data</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-06-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>This paper in markdown format was written by Ethan White et al.
    The markdown file and the associated bibliogaphy and figure files
    are available from the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/weecology/data-sharing-paper">Github
    repository of the paper</ext-link>.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>I used
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/weecology/data-sharing-paper/commit/b5a73eb0942a18bb29810025a528aea48a8465e7">this</ext-link>
    version, an earlier version was published as
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.7v1">PeerJ
    Preprint</ext-link>. Special thanks to Ethan White for allowing me
    to reuse this paper. The paper is used here as an example document
    to show how markdown can handle scholarly documents, in particular
    tables, figures and citations. The document was slightly modified
    from the orginal: added YAML frontmatter (needed by jekyll, author
    names are also stored there), and changed the anchor text for some
    links. This post is using the APA citation style. Please restrict
    your comments to issues related to Scholarly Markdown, for the
    content of the article contact Ethan directly.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<sec id="abstract">
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>Sharing data is increasingly considered to be an important part of
  the scientific process. Making your data publicly available allows
  original results to be reproduced and new analyses to be conducted.
  While sharing your data is the first step in allowing reuse, it is
  also important that the data be easy to understand and use. We
  describe nine simple ways to make it easy to reuse the data that you
  share and also make it easier to work with it yourself. Our
  recommendations focus on making your data understandable, easy to
  analyze, and readily available to the wider community of
  scientists.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>Sharing data is increasingly recognized as an important component
  of the scientific process (Whitlock, McPeek, Rausher, Rieseberg, &amp;
  Moore, 2010). The sharing of scientific data is beneficial because it
  allows replication of research results and reuse in meta-analyses and
  projects not originally intended by the data collectors (Poisot,
  Mounce, &amp; Gravel, 2013). In ecology and evolutionary biology,
  sharing occurs through a combination of formal data repositories like
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/">GenBank</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datadryad.org/">Dryad</ext-link>,
  and through individual and institutional websites.</p>
  <p>While data sharing is increasingly common and straightforward, much
  of the shared data in ecology and evolutionary biology are not easily
  reused because they do not follow best practices in terms of data
  structure, metadata, and licensing (M. B. Jones, Schildhauer,
  Reichman, &amp; Bowers, 2006). This makes it more difficult to work
  with existing data and therefore makes the data less useful than it
  could be (M. B. Jones et al., 2006; O. J. Reichman, Jones, &amp;
  Schildhauer, 2011). Here we provide a list of 9 simple ways to make it
  easier to reuse the data that you share.</p>
  <p>Our recommendations focus on making your data understandable, easy
  to work with, and available to the wider community of scientists. They
  are designed to be simple and straightforward to implement, and as
  such represent an introduction to good data practices rather than a
  comprehensive treatment. We contextualize our recommendations with
  examples from ecology and evolutionary biology, though many of the
  recommendations apply broadly across scientific disciplines. Following
  these recommendations makes it easier for anyone to reuse your data
  including other members of your lab and even yourself.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="1-share-your-data">
  <title>1. Share your data</title>
  <p>The first and most important step in sharing your data is to share
  your data. The recommendations below will help make your data more
  useful, but sharing it in any form is a big step forward. So, why
  should you share your data?</p>
  <p>Data sharing provides substantial benefits to the scientific
  community (Fienberg &amp; Martin, 1985). It allows</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>the results of existing analyses to be reproduced and improved
      upon (Fienberg &amp; Martin, 1985; Poisot et al., 2013),</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>data to be combined in meta-analyses to reach general
      conclusions (Fienberg &amp; Martin, 1985),</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>new approaches to be applied to the data and new questions
      asked using it (Fienberg &amp; Martin, 1985), and</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>approaches to scientific inquiry that couldn’t even be
      considered without broad scale data sharing (Hampton et al.,
      2013).</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>As a result, data sharing is increasingly required by funding
  agencies (Poisot et al. (2013); e.g.,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsf.gov/bfa/dias/policy/dmp.jsp">NSF</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/notice-files/NOT-OD-03-032.html">NIH</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/Professors-Professeurs/FinancialAdminGuide-GuideAdminFinancier/Responsibilities-Responsabilites_eng.asp">NSERC</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fwf.ac.at/en/public_relations/oai/index.html">FWF</ext-link>),
  journals (Whitlock et al., 2010), and potentially by law (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doyle.house.gov/sites/doyle.house.gov/files/documents/2013%2002%2014%20DOYLE%20FASTR%20FINAL.pdf">FASTR</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>Despite these potential benefits to the community, many scientists
  are still reluctant to share data. This reluctance is largely due to
  perceived fears of 1) competition for publications based on the shared
  data, 2) technical barriers, and 3) a lack of recognition for sharing
  data (Hampton et al., 2013; Palmer et al., 2004). These concerns are
  often not as serious as they first appear, and the minimal costs
  associated with data sharing are frequently offset by individual
  benefits to the data sharer (Hampton et al., 2013; Parr &amp;
  Cummings, 2005). Many data sharing initiatives allow for data
  embargoes or limitations on direct competition that can last for
  several years while the authors develop their publications and thus
  avoid competition for deriving publications from the data. Also,
  logistical barriers to data sharing are diminishing as data archives
  become increasingly common and easy to use (Hampton et al., 2013; Parr
  &amp; Cummings, 2005). Datasets are now considered citable entities
  and data providers receive recognition in the form of increased
  citation metrics and credit on CVs and grant applications (Heather A
  Piwowar &amp; Vision, 2013; Heather A. Piwowar, Day, &amp; Fridsma,
  2007; Poisot et al., 2013). In addition to increased citation rates,
  shared datasets that are documented and standardized are also more
  easily reused in the future by the original investigator. As a result,
  it is increasingly beneficial to the individual researcher to share
  data in the most useful manner possible.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-provide-metadata">
  <title>2. Provide metadata</title>
  <p>The first key to using data is understanding it. Metadata is
  information about the data including how it was collected, what the
  units of measurement are, and descriptions of how to best use the
  data. Clear metadata makes it easier to figure out if a dataset is
  appropriate for a project. It also makes data easier to use by both
  the original investigators and by other scientists by making it easy
  to figure out how to work with the data. Without clear metadata,
  datasets can be overlooked or not used due to the difficulty of
  understanding the data (Fraser &amp; Gluck, 1999; A. S. Zimmerman,
  2003), and the data becomes less useful over time (Michener, Brunt,
  Helly, Kirchner, &amp; Stafford, 1997).</p>
  <p>Metadata can take several forms, including descriptive file and
  column names, a written description of the data, images
  (<italic>i.e.,</italic> maps, photographs), and specially structured
  information that can be read by computers. Good metadata should
  provide 1) the what, when, where, and how of data collection, 2) how
  to find and access the data, 3) suggestions on the suitability of the
  data for answering specific questions, 4) warnings about known
  problems or inconsistencies in the data, and 5) information to check
  that the data are properly imported, such as the number of rows and
  columns in the dataset and the total sum of numerical columns
  (Michener et al., 1997; Strasser, Cook, Michener, &amp; Budden, 2012;
  A. S. Zimmerman,</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
