<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>OAI-PMH: Interview with Tony Hammond</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-05-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Most of us find, store and sometimes read scientific papers
electronically. Although abstracts and full-text papers are usually
available as web pages in HTML format, PDF is clearly the preferred
format for storing and printing papers.</p>
<p>But publishing scientific papers in electronic form obviously
requires more than providing the content in HTML or PDF format. We want
to find the papers we are interested in on the journal homepage or in a
digital library (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.pubmed.gov/">PubMed</ext-link>),
and for this we need metadata about the paper. The metadata could simply
be an digital object identifier
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.doi.org/">DOI</ext-link>),
but the metadata could also contain important information required to
find a paper in a search strategy (e.g. authors, title, publication date
or keywords).</p>
<p>As
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://network.nature.com/people/duncan/profile">Duncan
Hull</ext-link> <italic><italic>et al.</italic></italic> noted in a
<italic><italic>PLoS Computational Biology</italic></italic> paper last
year
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000204">Defrosting
the digital library: bibliographic tools for the next generation
web</ext-link>), metadata are often disconnected from the data, and
there are no universally agreed standards to represent these
metadata.</p>
<p>But why should we as scientists care about the technologies used to
publish and distribute a paper? We shouldn't forget that these
technologies could allow new and innovative ways to find and read
scientific papers. One simple example: storing the metadata in the PDF
file (using
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/2008/12/xmp_labelling_for_nature.html">XMP</ext-link>)
could make it much easier to import a large collection of PDF files into
a reference manager.</p>
<p>One such initiative to provide the metadata of a scientific paper is
OAI-PMH. I asked Tony Hammond from Nature.com a few questions about this
newly supported protocol, as well as some more general questions about
metadata provided by the Nature Publishing Group journals.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-oai-pmh-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what OAI-PMH is and does?</title>
  <p>Well, we'll first need to unpack that double acronym. OAI-PMH is
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/pmh/">Protocol
  for Metadata Harvesting</ext-link> which comes from the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/">Open
  Archives Initiative</ext-link>. It's traditionally been known simply
  as OAI, although these days it's more properly referred to in full as
  OAI-PMH in view of the arrival of a new sibling protocol: OAI-ORE,
  which stands for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/ore/">Object
  Reuse and Exchange</ext-link>. The two protocols are complementary:
  OAI-PMH deals with metadata harvesting, while OAI-ORE is concerned
  with content aggregation and compound digital objects.</p>
  <p>In brief, OAI-PMH provides an interoperability framework for
  networked repositories to exchange metadata records on their holdings.
  Such metadata typically includes bibliographic-type descriptions of
  repository items, such as title, authors and other identifying
  information. At a technical level OAI-PMH provides a very simple
  Web-based API for querying a repository by item, by set of items or by
  date range with data records being returned in an XML format which can
  be validated by a W3C XML Schema. A basic metadata format using
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://dublincore.org/">Dublin
  Core</ext-link> is available from all OAI-PMH implementations, while
  other richer community-specific metadata formats are encouraged for a
  fuller semantic exchange.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-is-prism-aggregator-message-pam-">
  <title>2. What is PRISM Aggregator Message (PAM)?</title>
  <p>I posted an entry
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.crossref.org/CrossTech/2009/05/post_2.html">PRISM
  Aggregator Message</ext-link> on CrossTech recently which delved into
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.idealliance.org/industry_resources/intelligent_content_informed_workflow/about_the_prism_aggregator_message">PRISM
  Aggregator Message</ext-link> (PAM) format and provided some specific
  details and also reasons why we chose to use it. Basically our choice
  of PAM stems from our earlier work with RSS and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://prismstandard.org/">PRISM</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Our first foray into semantic descriptions was with RSS feeds.
  While still at Elsevier I had collaborated with Timo Hannay and Ben
  Lund at Nature Publishing Group and wrote up a piece for
  <italic><italic>XML.com</italic></italic> entitled
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.xml.com/lpt/a/1252">Why
  Choose RSS 1.0?</ext-link> which described how journal RSS feeds could
  be enhanced with PRISM metadata. Specifically that piece reviewed the
  different RSS strains and came out strongly in favour of RSS 1.0 which
  being an RDF application was truly extensible and could accommodate
  new vocabularies. The identification of PRISM as a useful vocabulary
  was largely based on noting the adjacency of two RDF use cases in an
  early edition of the W3C RDF Primer: RSS and PRISM. I had been reading
  up on RSS and RDF and I suddenly thought “Bingo!”, we can add in PRISM
  terms to the RSS feeds since PRISM is a very handy supplement to
  Dublin Core and provides support for enumerated fields such as volume,
  issue, and page number. Another advantage for publishers was that
  PRISM is a simple term set and did not require any specialist library
  knowledge. A later paper by the same authors
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.dlib.org/dlib/december04/hammond/12hammond.html">The
  Role of RSS in Science Publishing</ext-link> published with
  <italic><italic>D-Lib Magazine</italic></italic> made a more in-depth
  review of RSS in scholarly publishing and concluded again that RSS 1.0
  with its transparent support for new vocabularies such as PRISM was
  the right way to go.</p>
  <p>We wanted to provide this standard article description that we were
  shipping with RSS also with OAI-PMH records. Unfortunately we could
  not simply move over the RDF properties into an OAI-PMH delivered
  RDF/XML payload. The problem with OAI-PMH is that it requires a record
  to be constrained by a W3C XML Schema. This is where
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.idealliance.org/industry_resources/intelligent_content_informed_workflow/about_the_prism_aggregator_message">PRISM
  Aggregator Message</ext-link> (PAM) comes in.</p>
  <p>PAM is an application of PRISM and defines a W3C XML Schema for XML
  content aggregators to use. The message is simply structured as a
  sequence of one or more articles each with a body section for XHTML
  content and a head section with PRISM metadata. The body sections are
  optional so PAM can be used exclusively as a simple metadata packaging
  format as we have chosen to implement for OAI-PMH.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-how-does-pam-relate-to-the-nlm-dtd">
  <title>3. How does PAM relate to the NLM DTD?</title>
  <p>Well, both are schemas for content. This was my blind spot with
  regard to PAM for many years. Our focus was on metadata exchange.
  PRISM was a vocabulary for metadata, or rather a set of closely
  related vocabularies. No problem. And yet there was this thing called
  PAM which was busying itself with content. And we had no interest in
  that as we had our own Nature-specific DTD. But the PRISM folks were
  very enthusiastic – so clearly there was a need.</p>
  <p>It only dawned on me relatively slowly that the PAM DTD (also
  available in W3C XML Schema form since PRISM 2.0) was the
  correspondent of the NLM DTD in the scholarly world. It provides an
  interchange format for content elements. So the real impetus behind
  the development of the PRISM metadata vocabularies was as a direct
  support to XML content exchange although content is not actually
  required to be present and the metadata alone can be used in dif</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
