<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>PLoS One: Interview with Peter Binfield</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-08-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>At
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/07/10/i-was-at-scibarcamp-palo-alto">SciBar
Camp Palo Alto last month</ext-link>, Peter Binfield from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/">PLoS
ONE</ext-link> gave a very interesting presentation on
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://friendfeed.com/scibarcamp/3577ed2e/peter-binfield-article-level-metric-from-plos">Article-level
metrics from the PLoS perspective</ext-link>. Particularly interesting
was his announcement that <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic>
journals will provide usage data (HTML pageviews, PDF and XML downloads)
for all their articles in September. Usage data, like
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0006022">all
measures of scientific impact</ext-link>, have their problems, but they
are a welcome addition to citation-based metrics.</p>
<p>I’ve interviewed Pete to ask him not only about article-level
metrics, but also about the publishing model of <italic><italic>PLoS
ONE</italic></italic> and how these two relate to each other.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-plos-one-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what PLoS ONE is and does?</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/">PLoS
  ONE</ext-link> is an Open Access, scholarly, peer reviewed journal for
  all of science. We will be three years old in December 2009, but
  already we are the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://poeticeconomics.blogspot.com/2009/07/dramatic-growth-of-plos-one-soon-to-be.html">third
  largest journal (of any type) in the world</ext-link>, publishing
  approximately 4,600 articles in 2009 alone and almost doubling in
  volume every year. We are online only (publishing in HTML, XML and
  PDF) and we publish daily (about 20 articles a day at present). In my
  view <italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic> is the most dynamic,
  innovative and exciting journal in the world, and I am proud to work
  on it.</p>
  <p>In many ways <italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic> operates
  like any other journal however it diverges in several important
  respects. The founding principle of <italic><italic>PLoS
  ONE</italic></italic> was that there are certain aspects of publishing
  which are best conducted pre-publication and certain aspects which are
  best conducted post-publication. The advent of online publishing has
  allowed us to take a step back and re-evaluate these aspects of how we
  publish research, without the burden of centuries of tradition. In
  this way, we have been able to experiment with new ways of doing
  things which may result in dramatic improvements in the entire process
  of scholarly publication.</p>
  <p>The most important thing which has come out of this premise is that
  unlike almost every other journal in the world, we make no judgment
  call whatsoever on the “impact” or “significance” or “interest level”
  of any submission. What this means is that if an article appropriately
  reports on well-conducted science, and if it passes our peer review
  process (which determines whether it deserves to join the scientific
  literature) then we will publish it. In this way, no author should
  ever receive the message that their article is scientifically sound
  but “not interesting enough” for our journal, or that their article is
  “only suited to a specialized audience”. As a result, we short circuit
  the vicious cycle of submit to a “top tier” journal; get reviewed; get
  rejected; submit to the next journal down the list; repeat until
  accepted and we are therefore able to place good science into the
  public domain as promptly as possible, with the minimum of burden on
  the academic community.</p>
  <p>The most recent example of the way in which we separate
  pre-publication activity from post-publication activity is with the
  development of our
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://everyone.plos.org/tag/article-level-metrics/">Article-Level
  Metrics program</ext-link>. <italic><italic>Article-level
  metrics</italic></italic> start from the assumption that the best way
  to measure the worth of an article is to look at the actual article
  itself (and not the journal it happens to have been published in).
  Following from this, it seems obvious that the best way to evaluate
  any article is to make use of the collective opinion of all experts in
  the field (and not a small number of peer reviewers, or a small number
  of people who ultimately go on to cite the article). An evaluation of
  this type (which requires that people actually read, and then act in a
  variety of ways, on the article) can only be done after the article is
  published (and not before, as happens when a journal rejects a paper
  because it thinks it is not “impactful” enough). Therefore, our
  development of new tools to facilitate the post-publication evaluation
  of individual articles is a great example of us separating out what is
  most appropriately conducted pre-publication vs post-publication.</p>
  <p>I have gone into some detail on these issues in a recent peer
  reviewed paper –
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://conferences.aepic.it/index.php/elpub/elpub2009/paper/view/114">PLoS
  One: background, future development, and article-level
  metrics</ext-link> and I would also recommend Shirley Wu’s excellent
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://shirleywho.wordpress.com/2009/08/06/the-evolution-of-scientific-impact/">recent
  blog post on this topic</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-can-you-describe-what-ambra-topaz-is-and-does">
  <title>2. Can you describe what Ambra/Topaz is and does?</title>
  <p>Basically Ambra is our publishing platform, which runs on top of
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://everyone.plos.org/2009/05/13/all-plos-titles-now-on-the-same-publishing-platform/">Topaz</ext-link>
  infrastructure. For the full technical detail, the best information is
  found
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://ambraproject.org/">here</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-can-you-talk-a-little-bit-more-about-the-post-publication-features-of-ambra-topaz">
  <title>3. Can you talk a little bit more about the post-publication
  features of Ambra/Topaz?</title>
  <p>Once an article is published, our platform allows users to leave
  feedback directly on the article. We were among the first journals to
  allow this, and we remain somewhat unique in this respect, although
  the concept is gaining broader acceptance and similar functionality is
  starting to appear at other publishers sites. Specifically, we allow
  users to leave a Note inline with a specific selection of text; or
  they can leave a general Comment on the entire article; or they can
  Star rate the article (on a 5 point scale in 3 categories). Comments
  and Notes form discussion threads, and users can then engage in debate
  on the points raised.</p>
  <p>Users may not be anonymous, they must follow our guidelines for
  civilized academic debate, and when leaving feedback they are
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/static/commentGuidelines.action">asked
  to declare any competing interests</ext-link>. I want to make it clear
  that the post-publication functionality that we provide is not
  intended to provide post-publication peer review – it is
  post-publication discourse and feedback. All
  <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> titles now share this same
  functionality.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-are-other-publishers-besides-plos-using-the-ambra-topaz-platform">
  <title>4. Are other publishers besides PLoS using the Ambra/Topaz
  platform?</title>
  <p>None that we are aware of although the NIH has an internal project.
  But Topaz is open source, so please contact us if you want to use
  it!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-article-level-metrics-does-plos-one-provide">
  <title>5. What article-level metrics does PLoS ONE provide?</title>
  <p>As of today (August 2009), on every article, in every
  <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> title we provide:</p>
  <p>Number of citations (as measured by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.scopus.com/">Scopus</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/">PubMedCentral</ext-link>)</p>
  <p>Number of social bookmarks (as recorded by</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
